(八代)＜一つ 昔の話をしようか＞
Shall I tell you a story about my past?
＜僕が
小学６年生だったころの話だ＞
About when I was in sixth grade...
あるときクラスメートの女子がハムスターが
７～８匹入った箱を 僕のところに持ってきた
Once, a girl, one of my classmates,
brought a box of seven
or eight hamsters over by me.
＜不注意から繁殖させてしまい
They had bred after she'd been careless,
それ以上 飼うことができなくなって途方に暮れていた＞
and now she was at a loss,
unable to take care of them all.
引き取った僕は うちに帰ると果実酒用の大瓶に水を入れて
ハムスターを 全て中に落とした
I agreed to take them.
On the way home, I filled up
an empty large fruit wine bottle
and drowned all of the hamsters in it.
＜３時間後 夕食を終えて 部屋に戻った僕は
その光景に 目を奪われた＞
Three hours later, after dinner,
I went to my room,
where I was captivated by what I saw.
＜そこには 力尽きて浮いている
他のハムスターの上を渡り歩く１匹のハムスターがいた＞
One hamster, treading water
above the other floating, lifeless hamsters.
＜正直 しびれた＞
To be honest, it excited me.
＜僕は そいつをスパイスと名付け
飼育することにした＞
I named the survivor Spice
and decided to raise it.
＜その光景を見たとき僕は
『蜘蛛の糸』という 短編小説を思い出した＞
The moment I saw it in there,
I thought of the short story,
"The Spider's Thread."
＜知っているかな？
Do you know it?
悪行の限りを尽くして地獄に落とされた カンダタという男に１匹の蜘蛛を助けたという
生前 唯一の善行によって釈迦が極楽から 蜘蛛の糸を垂らしてやった＞
A sinner named Kandata is in Hell
one day when Shakyamuni,
moved by the single compassionate
act of his life, sparing a spider's life,
lowers a spider's thread
down from Heaven to him.
＜カンダタは 極楽を目指して 登り始めるが
他の亡者たちが 後を追ってくると 次々と蹴落とした＞
Kandata begins climbing
towards Heaven,
kicking down at his fellow sinners
when they try to climb up after him.
＜すると…＞
＜糸は切れ カンダタは
再び 地獄へと落ちていった＞
Then the thread snaps,
and Kandata falls back down to Hell.
＜こんな話 信じてもらえるとは
思わないんだけどあえて言うよ＞
I don't think you'll believe this,
but I'll tell you anyway.
＜いや 君なら
分かってくれるかもしれない＞
Or maybe you will understand.
＜スパイスと出会って以来僕には
蜘蛛の糸が 見えるようになった＞
Since I became acquainted with Spice,
it's as if I could see the spider's thread.
＜それが見えた人間を
殺してきた＞
I've murdered the people
who I could see were connected to it.
＜だけど あるとき 一人の少年が
僕の計画を阻止した＞
But at some point,
a boy disrupted my plans.
＜そして その少年の頭の上にも
蜘蛛の糸が現れた＞
And then I saw a spider's thread
attached to the top of his head, too.
(悟)八代！
Yashiro!
≪俺は お前の未来を知ってるぞ！
I know your future!
＜しかし
彼は 死ぬことはなかった＞
But he didn't die.
＜僕は そいつに スパイスと名付けて観察することにした＞
I named him Spice
and began observing him.
I'm talking about you, Satoru.
＜それが君だよ 悟＞
ERASED
(佐知子)
お会計は 987円になります｡
That'll be 987 yen.
ありがとうございます｡
Thank you.
ICHI REAL ESTATE
(佐知子)《そういえば
悟が いつか言ってたっけ》
Come to think of it,
didn't Satoru tell me once...
《ホントはさ 上野には
電車１本で行けるんだ》
The fact is, you can go to Ueno
without changing trains.
(佐知子)《ホントだ》
It's true.
《あの言葉は
何だったんだべ…》
What was that about?
FIGHT, WONDER GUY!
TV THEME SONG
(佐知子)おはよう 悟｡
Good morning, Satoru.
FUNABASHI GENERAL HOSPITAL
(北村)うん 驚きだ｡
とても 15年 眠っていたとは…｡
Yes. I'm surprised.
It's hard to believe
you were asleep for 15 years.
Fif... teen... years...
じゅう… ご… ね…｡
Oh! You can speak.
(北村)ほう… 声が出たね｡
こりゃ リハビリを始める日も
遠くなさそうだ｡
I don't think you'll have to wait long
before starting rehab.
15年もの間 毎日 ４時間かけてお母さんは
僕の体を ケアし続けてくれたそうだ
Mom has spent four hours of every day
for the last 15 years caring for my body.
＜３年ほど前からは
ＥＭＳという装置を使い
For the last three years,
she's been using an EMS device
僕が目覚める日に備えていた＞
to prepare for the day when I woke up.
＜関節のケア 筋肉のケア＞
She took care of my joints
and my muscles.
小５のころ139cmだった
僕の身長は169cmになっていた
I was 139 cm tall in fifth grade,
and now I'm 169 cm tall.
＜北村先生は ｢お母さんのおかげ｣と
｢あり得ない｣を 交互に連発していた＞
Dr. Kitamura keeps saying,
"This is all because of your mother"
and "It's remarkable."
(北村)さて 悟君
そろそろ頃合いだと思う｡
Well, Satoru, I think
this is a good time for it.
次の質問に答えてくれ｡
Answer my next question.
君が眠りにつく前のことで
最後に覚えていることは 何かな？
What's the last thing you remember
before falling asleep?
(悟)最後に 覚えていること…｡
The last thing I remember...
《あれ？》
Huh?
《何だっけ？》
What was it again?
＜その記憶は 固く閉ざされた扉に
阻まれていた＞
That memory was blocked,
locked up tight behind a door.
(北村)見てみるかい？
Do you want to see yourself?
驚かないね｡
えっ？
Don't be shocked.
What?
11歳のころとは だいぶ
顔も変わってるはずなんだけど｡
Your face has changed a lot
since you were 11.
まあ 記憶が 混乱しているわけだし
自分というものに対する認識に 多少誤差が出てるのかも｡
Your memories are scrambled too,
so there may be discrepancies
regarding your sense of self.
＜そのときは そうなのかな
くらいに思っていた＞
At the time, I thought
maybe he was right,
＜けれど…＞
but even being in the Heisei era
for the first time,
《初めて見たはずの 平成という元号にも
何も違和感を覚えなかった》
nothing felt out of place.
PATIENCE
《我慢｡ 心拍計｡ 喪失感｡ 仲裁》
"Patience." "Heart rate monitor."
HEART RATE MONITOR
SENSE OF LOSS
"Sense of loss." "Arbitration."
ARBITRATION
《全部 読める…｡
いったい いつ覚えたんだ？》
I can read all of these words.
When in the world did I learn them?
BOYS' FLIGHT
《僕は 何なんだ？》
Who am I?
(佐知子)おはよう 悟｡
Good morning, Satoru.
おはよう｡
Good morning.
(佐知子)
悟 お客さんが来てくれたよ｡
Satoru, you've got visitors.
(ケンヤ)久しぶり 悟｡
(ヒロミ)悟君 元気そうだね｡
Long time no see, Satoru.
You look good, Satoru.
＜小林 賢也と 杉田 広美は
クラスで 特に仲の良かった２人だ＞
Kenya Kobayashi and Hiromi Sugita
were especially good friends of mine.
＜ケンヤは 弁護士
ヒロミは 医師だという＞
Kenya's a lawyer now,
and Hiromi's a doctor.
＜２人とは 他愛もない話をした＞
I talked with them about trivial things.
＜ケンヤは 僕に 何か尋ねたいようだったが
お母さんに 何か 言い含められていたのだと思う＞
It seemed that Kenya wanted
to ask me something,
but I think Mom had given him
strict instructions.
＜その日は ただ雑談に終始した＞
So we just chatted that day.
See you!
したっけ｡
(ヒロミ)したっけ｡
See you!
＜僕の方にも聞きたいことは たくさんあったけどどうも
お母さんは 僕の過去の話題を 避けているようだ＞
There were a lot of things
I wanted to ask them too,
but it seems Mom was trying
to avoid the topic of my past.
＜15年間 いつか目覚めると信じて
お母さんは 僕のためだけに生きてきた＞
Mom had been spending her life
for the past 15 years only for me,
having faith
that I would awaken one day.
お母さんが そう望んでいるなら
もう思い出さなくて いいんじゃないか？
If it's what Mom wishes,
I guess I don't have to remember.
うっ… ああ…｡
(看護師)大丈夫かい？
今日は ここまでにしようか｡
Are you okay?
Why don't we call it a day?
ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
≪悟｡
Satoru!
おめでとう 加代｡
Congratulations, Kayo.
Episode 11
Future
(雛月)今は 結婚して
杉田 加代になったよ｡
I got married.
My name is Kayo Sugita now.
ああ その子の父親ってヒロミ？
Your baby's father is Hiromi then?
(雛月)うん｡
Yeah.
ヒロミが 何か話したそうに してたのって
子供のことかな｡ (雛月)かも｡
It seemed like Hiromi wanted
to tell me something.
Maybe it was about your child.
Could've been.
そういえばヒロミに似て まつげ長いね｡
Come to think of it, the baby has
Hiromi's long eyelashes.
(雛月)うん 男の子だけどね｡名前は 未来｡
Yeah, even though he's a boy.
His name is Mirai.
未来か… いい名前だね｡
Mirai... The "future"...
That's a good name.
(雛月)悟…｡
ホントは 抵抗あったんだ｡
Satoru...
To be honest,
we felt kind of uncomfortable.
私たちだけ幸せになって
いいんだべかって｡
Thinking "Is it all right
for just us to become happy?"
(雛月)悟が眠ってしまったのは
私たちのことが 原因かもしれないのに｡
Even though we may have been
the cause of you being in a coma...
何だか…
悟を置き去りにするみたいで｡
It kind of felt...
like we were leaving you behind.
加代 僕の運命は 僕のものだ｡
Kayo, my fate is my own.
君が責任を感じる必要はないよ｡
There's no need for you
to feel responsible.
今の僕がこうなってるのはきっと僕自身が
望んだことの結果だ｡
I'm sure that what's become of me
was a result of something I wanted.
15年も寝てたくせに
口が達者だね｡
You were asleep for 15 years
but still have a silver tongue.
えっ？ ああ…｡
それでもね 悟｡
Even so, Satoru...
独りぼっちでいることしか 想像できなかった私が
今 こうして家族といられるのは 悟がいてくれたおかげだよ｡
Before, I could only imagine being alone,
but now I've got a family,
and it was all made possible
because of you.
ありがとう｡
Thank you.
《ありがとうか…》
Thank you...
《僕は いったい何を…》
What did I do?
よーしよし おなかすいたの？
よしよし｡
Okay, okay.
Are you hungry?
悟？ 大丈夫？
うん｡
Satoru?
Are you all right?
Yeah.
急に 色々 話してごめん｡
I'm sorry to spring all of this on you.
疲れさせちゃったね｡
I've tired you out.
じゃあ また来るから｡
Well, I'll visit again.
うん｡ したっけ｡
Yeah. See you later.
あら 悟 戻ってたの？
Oh, Satoru. You're back?
ああ｡
Yeah.
さっき 雛月が来たよ｡
Hinazuki was here a little while ago.
うん｡ 私も会った｡
赤ちゃん めんこかったね～｡
Yeah. I saw her too.
Her baby's adorable, isn't he?
あのさ お母さん｡
Listen...
Mom...
なあに？
Yes?
あいつら また来てる｡
They're here again.
何？
What is it?
ゴシップ誌のカメラマン｡
Photographers for gossip rags.
15年間 眠ってた あんたのことを
記事にしたいんだべさ｡
They want to write articles
about you being in a coma for 15 years.
ふ～ん｡
ああ そういや 悟｡
Oh, that's right, Satoru...
何か話あるの？
You were going to tell me something?
いや… 何でもないよ｡
No, it was nothing.
(佐知子)どうぞ｡
Come in.
こんにちは｡
Hello.
(佐知子)お世話になっております｡
Thank you for everything.
北村先生 僕 いつごろ
歩けるようになるんですか？
Dr. Kitamura, when will I
be able to walk again?
(北村)さあね 君しだいかな｡
I don't know.
That could depend on you.
じゃあ 今日からリハビリの量を
倍にしてください｡
Then from today, please let me
do twice as much rehab.
えっ？
早く 外を歩きたいんです｡
I'm anxious to walk outside.
あっ ああ…｡ 考えておくよ｡
I'll think about it.
ちょっと失礼｡
Excuse me a minute.
(北村)ええ｡
ありがとうございます 理事｡
Yes, thank you, Director.
順調に回復しています｡
He's making a smooth recovery.
いつ記憶を取り戻しても
おかしくない状態です｡
He could regain
his memories at any time.
No.
いえ 先日もお話ししたとおり
その件は お断りいたします｡
As I said the other day,
I have to refuse that.
私の患者は
マウスではありませんので…！
My patient isn't a mouse—
(北村)失礼します｡
SATORU FUJINUMA
Excuse me.
(看護師)すごいじゃないか 悟君！
だいぶ 手足の筋力が上がったね｡
Amazing, Satoru!
Your arms and legs
have gotten a lot stronger.
(看護師)おめでとう 悟君！
(看護師)すごいよ 藤沼さん！
Congratulations, Satoru!
That was great, Mr. Fujinuma!
You really walked all that way!
本当に歩ききるなんて｡
(看護師)よく頑張ったね｡
It was an awesome effort!
(佐知子)悟 ケンヤ君が
お見舞いに来てくれたわよ｡
Satoru, Kenya is here to see you.
やあ ケンヤ｡
(ケンヤ)こんな時間に ごめんよ｡
Hi, Kenya.
Sorry to bother you now.
わざわざ来てくれて ありがとう｡
No, thank you for coming.
(澤田)こんにちは 悟君｡
Hello, Satoru.
初めまして…｡
Nice to meet you.
(澤田)お母さんの元同僚でね
I used to work with your mother.
君が小学校に上がる前に何度か会ったことがあるんだが｡
We met several times
before you started elementary school.
もう20年以上前だもの
いくら何でも 覚えてないべさ｡
That was over 20 years ago.
He could never remember that.
(ケンヤ)じゃあ また来るから｡
(澤田)お大事に｡
Well, I'll visit again.
Take care.
(澤田)15年も待ったんだ｡
いまさら焦っても仕方ないさ｡
We've waited 15 years for this.
There's no need to be impatient now.
まっ ゆっくりやろう｡
(ケンヤ)ええ｡
Let's take it slowly.
Agreed.
ん？
こんにちは｡
Hello.
I see.
そうか 久美ちゃん
再来週 手術なのか｡
So you've got surgery
the week after next, Kumi.
(久美)お姉ちゃんから
骨髄っていう血をもらうの｡
My sister is going to
give me her bone marrow.
それで治るんだって｡
They say that's what's going to cure me.
でもね… 怖いんだ｡
But...
I'm scared.
(久美)
《15年も眠ってたって 本当？》
Is it true you were asleep for 15 years?
久美ちゃんが この病院に来てから
もう３カ月くらいたつね｡
You've been here
for about three months, huh, Kumi?
Yeah.
うん｡
久美ちゃんに カｯコイイところ
見せようって頑張ってきたからな｡
I've been trying all this time
to look good in front of you.
いなくなると
張り合いなくなるよ｡
I'll be really disappointed
once you're out of here.
勇気｡
Courage.
えっ？
勇気の出し方 教えようか？
Want me to tell you
how to muster up courage?
大切な人の笑顔を
思い浮かべるんだ｡
You picture the smiling face
of someone who's dear to you.
もちろん 君も笑顔でね｡
Of course, you have to smile too.
(男性)時の放浪者｡
Time's drifter...
15年間 眠ってた男の幼女趣味｡
He wakes up after 15 years,
is interested in little girls,
心は子供 体は大人 退院間近!?
is a kid at heart with an adult's body,
and he may be released soon.
ってのは どうよ？
(男性)いいね｡
How do you like that angle?
Nice.
うわっ！
≪病院内で 一般人の盗撮｡
名誉毀損｡ 住居侵入｡
Secretly taking photos
of a civilian in the hospital...
Defamation, trespassing...
じゅうぶん
刑事処罰の対象になる｡
Plenty to warrant punishment by law.
さっさと出ていきたまえ｡
Get your asses out of here.
すっごく奇麗な
お花だったんだよ｡
The flowers were beautiful.
西園さん！ こんにちは｡
Mr. Nishizono!
Hello!
やあ 久美ちゃん｡
Hi, Kumi.
(西園)藤沼 悟君｡
えっ？ ええ｡
Satoru Fujinuma...
Yes...
(西園)僕だよ｡
忘れてしまったかな？
It's me. Have you forgotten?
いや 僕の方も
だいぶ 変わったからな｡
Well, I've changed a lot.
ほら 小学校５年生のとき 担任だった八代 学だよ｡
Here, I was your
homeroom teacher in fifth grade.
Gaku Yashiro.
(八代)今は
西園と名乗っているんだ｡
I go by "Nishizono" now.
下の名前も ｢まなぶ｣にした｡
I changed my given name to "Manabu."
どうして 名前を変えたんですか？
Why did you change your name?
(八代)実は ５年前に結婚してね｡
婿養子に入ったんだ｡
Actually, I got married five years ago
and was adopted into her
family as a son-in-law.
へぇ…｡
(八代)妻のお父さんは長く市議会議員を やっていたんだが
３年前に亡くなってね｡
My father-in-law was a city council
member for many years,
but he passed away three years ago.
その地盤を引き継ぐ形で
市議になった｡
I inherited his constituency
and joined the council myself.
そのタイミングで 下の名前も
読みやすいように変えたんだ｡
That's when I changed
my given name,
keeping the kanji but going
with the more common reading.
じゃあ 今は 政治家なの？
So you're a politician now?
(八代)まだ１年生議員だけどね｡
Still a freshman council member though.
でも八代先生なら
立派な政治家に なれそうな気がする｡
But I have a feeling you'll make
a great politician, Mr. Yashiro.
久美ちゃんとは 白血病の
ﾁｬﾘﾃｨｰｲﾍﾞﾝﾄで知り合ってね｡
I met Kumi at a charity event
for leukemia.
たまたま この病院の理事が
知人だったんで 紹介したんだ｡
The director of this hospital is my
acquaintance, and he introduced us.
そうだったんですか｡
Oh, really?
(八代)君が目覚めたことは
もっと前に知ったんだけどね｡
I found out you'd regained
consciousness some time before that.
すっかり お見舞いが
遅くなってしまった｡
It took me long enough
to pay you a visit.
今日は わざわざ僕のために？
You went out of your way to visit me?
(八代)この15年間 君が
目覚めるのを心待ちにしていた｡
I'd been anticipating
your awakening for 15 years.
あっ… ありがとう｡
Thank you.
(八代)
君とは 色々あったじゃないか｡
You must've been through a lot.
ごめんなさい 僕…｡
I'm sorry. I...
(八代)ああ 聞いてるよ｡
Yes, I've heard.
まだ記憶が
完全には 戻ってないんだろ？
You haven't regained
all of your memories, right?
おいおい 思い出していけばいい｡
Remembering them gradually is best.
(八代)やあ｡
Hi.
八代先生｡
Mr. Yashiro...
君も 久美ちゃんのところに？
Are you also going to see Kumi?
Yes. Her surgery is scheduled
for the day after tomorrow,
ええ｡ あさって手術で自由に会えるのは
今日までだって聞いたから｡
and this is the last day
she can have visitors.
(八代)ああ 僕も 今 会ってきたところだ｡
といっても よく眠っていて 話せなかったがね｡
Yes. I just saw her now.
That being said, she was sleeping,
so I couldn't talk to her.
そうですか｡
じゃあ 後にしようかな｡
Oh, really?
Then maybe I'll try again later.
せっかくだし
ちょっと話しませんか？
Since you're here,
do you have time to chat?
(八代)ああ｡ ゴシップ誌のやつらに
邪魔をされても あれだし 場所を変えようか｡
Sure, but I don't want to be interrupted
by the gossip mag hounds,
so why don't we go somewhere else?
(八代)
実は いい場所を見つけたんだ｡
I found the perfect place.
DELIVERIES
知らなかっただろ？
こんなエレベーターがあるなんて｡
You didn't know
about this elevator, did you?
ちょっとした冒険じゃないか｡
This is kind of an adventure, isn't it?
屋上を押してもらっていいかい？
Would you push the roof button?
残念｡
Too bad...
晴れていたら
夕日が奇麗なんだけどな｡
If it'd been a clear day,
the sunset would've been beautiful.
でも ここなら
変なカメラマンも来ないだろう｡
But there won't be any weird
photographers up here.
ホントは 立ち入り禁止だから
誰にも言うなよ｡
The roof is really off limits,
so don't tell anyone.
そういえば 悟も よく ケンヤやヒロミたちと
アジトへ行こうって 秘密基地ごっこをしてたよな｡
I'm reminded of how you,
Kenya and Hiromi often said,
"Let's go to the hideout!"
Your pretend secret base, right?
八代｡
Yashiro...
俺の記憶は戻っているぞ｡
I have...
my memories back!
♬～